<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>archie94.github.io/blogs/</title>
   
   <link>http://archie94.github.io/blogs/</link>
   <description>My digital notebook.</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> Arka Prava Basu</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>Skip newline character while reading from Scanner class</title>
	  <link>/blogs//skip-newline-while-reading-from-scanner-class</link>
	  <author>Arka Prava Basu</author>
	  <pubDate>2018-06-04T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blogs//skip-newline-while-reading-from-scanner-class</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>We have all come across reading from <code class="highlighter-rouge">stdin</code> while programming in Java and <code class="highlighter-rouge">java.util.Scanner</code> class provides easy way to parse expressions and give out primitive types. From the doc :</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>A Scanner breaks its input into tokens using a delimiter pattern, which by default matches whitespace. The resulting tokens may then be converted into values of different types using the various next methods.
</code></pre>
</div>

<p>So let’s look at the following code:</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>Scanner scanner = new Scanner(System.in);

int n = scanner.nextInt();

while(n-- &gt; 0) {
    String s = scanner.nextLine();
    System.out.println(s);
}
</code></pre>
</div>

<p>Clearly this piece of code spits out the words we type in. The first input should be a <code class="highlighter-rouge">Integer</code> denoting number of lines to take as user input. So for the input</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>3
asdf qwerty
Hello World
Hello java
</code></pre>
</div>

<p>we have the output</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>asdf qwerty
Hello World
</code></pre>
</div>

<p>Why is that? Experienced folks are quick to catch that the <code class="highlighter-rouge">scanner.nextInt()</code> does not consume the newline character. Workaround? Easy forcibly consume the newline character after the <code class="highlighter-rouge">scanner.nextInt()</code> read. Something like</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>Scanner scanner = new Scanner(System.in);

int n = scanner.nextInt();
scanner.nextLine();

while(n-- &gt; 0) {
    String s = scanner.nextLine();
    System.out.println(s);
}
</code></pre>
</div>

<p>And we get what we want. Another workaround: read the whole line and then parse it as an integer. Something like</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>try {
    n = Integer.parseInt(scanner.nextLine());
} catch (NumberFormatException e) {
    e.printStackTrace();
}
</code></pre>
</div>

<p>Works!</p>

<p>But recently I came across the <code class="highlighter-rouge">skip()</code> method available in the <code class="highlighter-rouge">Scanner</code> class. It works by taking in a pattern/regex and will skip the input that matches the said pattern. So lets do this</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>Scanner scanner = new Scanner(System.in);

int n = scanner.nextInt();
scanner.skip("(\r\n|[\n\r\u2028\u2029\u0085])?");

while(n-- &gt; 0) {
    String s = scanner.nextLine();
    System.out.println(s);
}
</code></pre>
</div>

<p>Whoa! Works but what did I just do? Well we are just telling scanner to skip any newline character after the interger read. Well why the whole <code class="highlighter-rouge">"(\r\n|[\n\r\u2028\u2029\u0085])?"</code>? Interestingly line break control character is different for different OS! Linux has <code class="highlighter-rouge">\n</code> escape sequence, Mac has <code class="highlighter-rouge">\r</code> while windows keeps <code class="highlighter-rouge">\r\n</code>. The stated pattern asks the <code class="highlighter-rouge">Scanner</code> class to remove them. Additionally</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>\u2028 is Unicode character LINE SEPARATOR
\u2029 is Unicode character PARAGRAPH SEPARATOR
\u0085 is Unicode character NEXT LINE (NEL)
</code></pre>
</div>

<p>This piece of code looked elegant to me; we are skipping the newline knowing what we can except although agreed maybe the previous method are more memorable. A big thanks to <a href="https://www.hackerrank.com/dashboard">Hackerrank</a>; found this piece of code in their prefilled code for <a href="https://www.hackerrank.com/challenges/string-construction/problem">String Construction</a> problem.</p>

<p>Cheers!</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Setting up Travis CI for the blog</title>
	  <link>/blogs//setting-up-travis-ci</link>
	  <author>Arka Prava Basu</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-06-05T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blogs//setting-up-travis-ci</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>If your blog is a fork of <a href="https://github.com/biomadeira/jasper/">Jasper</a> and you host it in github then you might have noticed that author pages and tag pages returns 404 error. The reasion as mentioned in this <a href="https://github.com/biomadeira/jasper/issues/16">issue</a> is that Github restricts running plugins for security reasons. <a href="https://github.com/biomadeira">Fábio Madeira</a> describes two workaround for this issue and here I am going to describe the second one.</p>

<p>Firstly in <code class="highlighter-rouge">_config.yml</code> we need to specify which repository we wish to build with travic-ci with the travis gem. The git url in github for any repository is of the form <code class="highlighter-rouge">https://github.com/USERNAME/REPO.git</code>.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Change username to your github username,</li>
  <li>repo to the name of the repository (for me it is blogs),</li>
  <li>branch to the name of the branch from which you want to build your project (I have kept it master),</li>
  <li>relative source is the path to your project w.r.t. the configuration file (since configuration file is mostly at the root of the project it will be <code class="highlighter-rouge">../PROJECT_NAME/</code>) and</li>
  <li>destination path where travis-ci will clone your project.</li>
  <li>After this change the production_url (for hosting in github it is <code class="highlighter-rouge">https://USERNAME.github.io/REPO</code>) and</li>
  <li>source_url (again should be of the form <code class="highlighter-rouge">https://github.com/USERNAME/REPO/</code>).</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="assets/images/s1.png" alt="Code" /></p>

<p>Now we need to create the <code class="highlighter-rouge">.travis.yml</code> file. Follow <a href="https://docs.travis-ci.com/user/languages/ruby/">this</a> to get started. Keep the ruby version to which you are using in your project. After this we need to generate a secure key with travis gem. First get your Github token from your Travis CI profile page.</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>	gem install travis
	travis encrypt 'GIT_NAME="YOUR_USERNAME" GIT_EMAIL="YOUR_EMAIL" GH_TOKEN=YOUR_TOKEN'
</code></pre>
</div>

<ul>
  <li><code class="highlighter-rouge">GIT_NAME</code> is your Github username,</li>
  <li>Obtain <code class="highlighter-rouge">GH_TOKEN</code> from <code class="highlighter-rouge">https://github.com/settings/tokens</code>.</li>
</ul>

<p>Add the secure key and specify the branch from where to build your project. Should look something like this:</p>

<p><img src="assets/images/s2.png" alt="Code" /></p>

<p>Travis CI should build from your specified branch every time you push after this setup!</p>

<p>After successful build got to <code class="highlighter-rouge">https://USERNAME.github.io/REPO</code> and see this time the author page and tag pages should work fine.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Blog of Blogs</title>
	  <link>/blogs//blog-of-blogs</link>
	  <author>Arka Prava Basu</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blogs//blog-of-blogs</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Here I plan to keep links of exciting blog posts which I encounter. I will go on updating the list regularly.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>A small and comprehensive <a href="https://johnleach.co.uk/words/323/git-submodules-in-n-easy-steps">blog</a> about getting acquainted with submodules in git.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Often an android device does not show up in ubuntu even though ADB has been enabled on the phone. The trick is to add your device to <code class="highlighter-rouge">udev</code> rules. Here is a good <a href="http://bernaerts.dyndns.org/android/339-android-oneplustwo-oneplusx-enable-adb-mtp-detection-ubuntu-trusty">tutorial</a> to do that. Alternatively go through the <a href="https://developer.android.com/studio/run/device.html">developer</a> page.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://ozzmaker.com/add-colour-to-text-in-python/">Add color to text in python</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.atlassian.com/git/tutorials/merging-vs-rebasing">Merging vs Rebasing in git</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/community/tutorials/how-to-install-apache-tomcat-7-on-ubuntu-14-04-via-apt-get">Install Apache Tomcat 7 on Ubuntu 14.04 via apt-get</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/raspberry_pi/comments/4skwiq/arch_linux_arm_tutorial_part_2_installing_sudo/?st=j3ag3dpv&amp;sh=537cfee1">Installing Sudo in Arch Linux ARM</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/community/tutorials/an-introduction-to-storage-terminology-and-concepts-in-linux">Introduction to strage terminology and concepts in Linux</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://keithschwarz.com">The Archive of Interesting Code</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="http://blog.jamesdbloom.com/JVMInternals.html">JVM Internals</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://www.joelonsoftware.com/2003/10/08/the-absolute-minimum-every-software-developer-absolutely-positively-must-know-about-unicode-and-character-sets-no-excuses/">Unicode and character sets</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=16838460">Interesting Tech Talks</a></p>
  </li>
</ol>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Working with submodules in Android Studio and git</title>
	  <link>/blogs//working-with-submodules-in-git-and-android-studio</link>
	  <author>Arka Prava Basu</author>
	  <pubDate>2017-02-01T10:18:00+00:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>/blogs//working-with-submodules-in-git-and-android-studio</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>I encountered working with submodules in Android Studio a while back while I was integrating GIS features with our <a href="https://github.com/sunny5125/pdm">PDM</a> app. Apparently it looked like a simple task, and truth be told it was, I did face a few hiccups getting there. The following will be a documentation of the procedure I followed while I integrated <a href="https://github.com/nextgis/android_gisapp">NextGis Android App</a> with our very own college project.</p>

<h3 id="the-basics">The Basics</h3>

<p>Android Studio provides the option to add sub modules to our existing project. What it means you can import another project (your own or maybe some other repository) and integrate it with your project with ease. As in my case I had to integrate <a href="https://github.com/nextgis/android_gisapp">this</a> repository. Looking closely you will observe that the NextGis android app repository has 2 submodules : <a href="https://github.com/nextgis/android_maplib">maplib</a> and <a href="https://github.com/nextgis/android_maplibui">maplibui</a>.</p>

<p>So I started out forking android_gisapp repository. In order to initialise the submodules within android_gisapp I had to do :</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>    git submodule init
    git submodule update
</code></pre>
</div>

<p>and voila, git clones the required submodules into android_gisapp and we are good to go. However for our research work we needed to change some core features of android_gisapp and soon realised it will be better to keep my own forks of maplib and maplibui.</p>

<p>At this point it is better to get acquainted with submodules in git, the best blog which I could find is <a href="https://johnleach.co.uk/words/323/git-submodules-in-n-easy-steps">here</a>. Changing the submodules in my fork of android_gisapp to point to my forks of maplib and maplibui was simple, just change the path in <code class="highlighter-rouge">.gitmodules</code> and do <code class="highlighter-rouge">git submodule update</code>. Finally push the changes.</p>

<h3 id="changing-a-project-to-build-as-a-library">Changing a project to build as a library</h3>

<p>This was the part in which I was stuck the most. I realised we cannot use an <code class="highlighter-rouge">apk</code> as a dependency in android project and it supports only <code class="highlighter-rouge">jar</code> and <code class="highlighter-rouge">aar</code> dependencies as of now. The alternative was to compile the android_gisapp as a library and include the <code class="highlighter-rouge">aar</code> file in dependency. I decided to keep my fork of android_gisapp as a module in our PDM app. That way we can change the submodules as we are developing PDM. So the project modules in PDM will look like</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>    app
     |
     |--android_gisapp
 	         |
 	         |--maplib
 	         |--maplibui
</code></pre>
</div>

<p>Before adding android_gisapp as a submodule since an android project cannot have two modules with same name I had to change the main module name of android_gispp from <code class="highlighter-rouge">app</code> to <code class="highlighter-rouge">android_gisapp</code>. To do this we can use the refractor option in android studio or change in <code class="highlighter-rouge">settings.gradle</code></p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>    include ':app', ':maplib', ':maplibui'
</code></pre>
</div>

<p>to</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>    include ':gisapp', ':maplib', ':maplibui'
</code></pre>
</div>

<p>After that I had to build android_gisapp as a library project. We cannot have two different apks for the same project and changes had to be made in this regard. To build project as a library head to <code class="highlighter-rouge">build.gradle</code> and change</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>    apply plugin: 'com.android.application'
</code></pre>
</div>

<p>to</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>    apply plugin: 'com.android.library'
</code></pre>
</div>

<p>We have to remove <code class="highlighter-rouge">applicationId</code> under <code class="highlighter-rouge">defaultConfig</code> and also the following section :</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>    applicationVariants.all { variant -&gt;
             variant.outputs.each { output -&gt;
                 output.outputFile = new File(output.outputFile.parent, "ngmobile-" + defaultConfig.versionName + ".apk")
             }
         }
</code></pre>
</div>

<p>Change category of the <code class="highlighter-rouge">LAUNCHER</code> activity to <code class="highlighter-rouge">DEFAULT</code> (in general it is likely that you will have a <code class="highlighter-rouge">LAUNCHER</code> activity in your main project)
Then do a fresh build of the project and push the changes to remote.</p>

<h3 id="adding-an-existing-repository-as-module-in-pdm">Adding an existing repository as module in PDM</h3>

<p>The next bit was simple. I had to include my fork of android_gisapp as a submodule in PDM. In PDM directory I had to</p>

<div class="highlighter-rouge"><pre class="highlight"><code>    git submodule add &lt;link to my fork of android_gisapp&gt;
    git init
    git submodule update
    cd android_gisapp
    git submodule init
    git submodule update
</code></pre>
</div>

<p>Then in Android Studio File-&gt;Project Structure-&gt;app-&gt;add a new module and give the path to android_gisapp. After that do a clean build.</p>

<p>Hopefully this integration was proper and meaningful. Upto now it has been all good. It is super easy to maintain all 4 repositories. Two noteworthy points are</p>

<ul>
  <li>always explicitely checkout to a branch in a submodule in git. Failure to do this may lead to HEAD detached.</li>
  <li>after commiting changes in submodules we must push them. Only after that we can add the changes and reflect them in parent module.</li>
</ul>

<p>Like all things in git, the learning curve is steep but there are immense possibilities to get out of it once we get the basic concepts. I will keep updating this thread if I have missed some part, for any major updates or changes I will make a separate blog. Till then adios!</p>

<h3 id="credits">Credits</h3>

<p>A very big shout out to <a href="http://nextgis.com/">NextGis</a> for keeping such a well documented repository to provide Opensource GIS application for android.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
